I'm a medical illustrator,
أنا أرسم للطب،
and I come from a slightly different point of view.
وأتيت من وجهة نظر مختلفة قليلاً.
I've been watching, since I grew up,
لقد كنت أراقب، منذ نشأتي،
the expressions of truth and beauty in the arts
تعابير الحقيقة والجمال في الفنون
and truth and beauty in the sciences.
والحقيقة والجمال في العلوم.
And while these are both wonderful things in their own right --
وبينما هذين شيئين جميلين في حد زاتهما--
they both have very wonderful things going for them --
لدى كلاهما أشياء مدهشة جداً ترمي اليهم--
truth and beauty as ideals that can be looked at by the sciences
الحقيقة والجمال كمُثل عليا يمكن النظر اليهما بواسطة العلوم
and by math are almost like the ideal conjoined twins
والرياضيات وهما مثل توأمين متطابقين ببراعة
that a scientist would want to date.
يود العلماء مواعدتهما.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
These are expressions of truth as awe-full things,
هذه تعابير الحقيقة كأشياء فظيعة،
by meaning they are things you can worship.
بالمعنى، هذه الأشياء التي يمكنك تقديسها.
They are ideals that are powerful. They are irreducible.
أنها مثالية بقوة، وهي غير قابلة للإختزال،
They are unique. They are useful --
وهي متفردة، و هي مفيدة--
sometimes, often a long time after the fact.
بعض الأحيان، دائماً وقت طويل، بعد الحقيقة.
And you can actually roll some of the pictures now,
ويمكنك إظهار بعض الصور الآن،
because I don't want to look at me on the screen.
لأنني لا أحب أن أرى نفسي في الشاشة.
Truth and beauty are things
الحقيقة والجمال هي الأشياء
that are often opaque to people who are not in the sciences.
التي غالبا ما تكون مبهمة بالنسبة للأشخاص الذين ليسوا في مجال العلوم.
They are things that describe beauty in a way
أنها الأمور التي تصف الجمال بطريقة
that is often only accessible if you understand the language
عادة تستطيعها اذا أمكنك فهم اللغة
and the syntax of the person
وبناء سياق الجمل للشخص
who studies the subject in which truth and beauty is expressed.
الذي درس المادة التي فيها الحقيقة والجمال مشروحة.
If you look at the math, E=mc squared,
اذا نظرت الى الرياضيات، المعادلة E= تربيع mc
if you look at the cosmological constant,
اذا نظرتم الى الثابت الكوني ،
where there's an anthropic ideal, where you see that life had to evolve
حيث هناك مثالية الانثروبي ، حيث ترى أن الحياة قد تتطورت
from the numbers that describe the universe --
من الأرقام التي تشرح الكون--
these are things that are really difficult to understand.
تلك هي الأشياء التي يصعب بالفعل فهمها.
And what I've tried to do
ولقد حاولت أن أفهمها
since I had my training as a medical illustrator --
من أن أخذت تدريبي كرسام طبي--
since I was taught animation by my father,
منذ أن علمني والدي الرسوم المتحركة،
who was a sculptor and my visual mentor --
الذي كان نحاتاً ومعلمي في البصريات--
I wanted to figure out a way to help people
أردت معرفة الطرق لمساعدة الناس
understand truth and beauty in the biological sciences
لفهم الحقيقة والجمال في العلوم الإحيائية
by using animation, by using pictures, by telling stories
بإستخدام الرسوم المتحركة، بإستخدام الصور، بسرد القصص.
so that the things that are not necessarily evident to people
اذاً تلك هي الأشياء التي ليست بالضرورة واضحة للناس
can be brought forth, and can be taught, and can be understood.
يمكن أن تخرج، ويمكن تدريسها، ويمكن فهمها.
Students today are often immersed in an environment
الطلاب اليوم عادة ما يكونوا مغمورين في بيئة
where what they learn is subjects that have truth and beauty
حيث يتعلمون المناهج التي تتضمن الحقيقة والجمال
embedded in them, but the way they're taught is compartmentalized
في داخلها، لكن الطرق التي يدرسون بها مجزأة
and it's drawn down to the point where the truth and beauty
وتساق دائماً الى نقطة حيث الحقيقة والجمال
are not always evident.
ليسوا دائماً واضحة.
It's almost like that old recipe for chicken soup
انها تقريبا مثل تلك الوصفة القديمة لحساء الدجاج ،
where you boil the chicken until the flavor is just gone.
حيث تقوم بسلق الدجاج حتى تضيع النكهة.
We don't want to do that to our students.
لا نريد أن نفعل ذلك لطلابنا.
So we have an opportunity to really open up education.
اذاً فلدينا فرصة حقيقية لتوسيع تعليمنا.
And I had a telephone call from Robert Lue at Harvard,
وقد تلقيت إتصالاً من روبرت ليو في هارفارد،
in the Molecular and Cellular Biology Department,
في شعبة الأحياء والطب الجزيئي،
a couple of years ago. He asked me if my team and I
قبل عدة أعوام. وقد سألني اذا ما كان فريقي وانا
would be interested and willing to really change
مهتمين وراغبين في تغيير كيف
how medical and scientific education is done at Harvard.
يتم تدريس الطب والتعليم العلمي في هارفارد حقيقةً.
So we embarked on a project that would explore the cell --
إذاً فقد شرعنا في مشروع سيقوم بإستكشاف الخلية ،
that would explore the truth and beauty inherent
الذي سيستكشف الحقيقة والجمال الموروث
in molecular and cellular biology
في الجزيئ والخلية البيولوجية
so that students could understand a larger picture
بحيث يستطيع الطلاب فهم الصورة الأكبر
that they could hang all of these facts on.
بحيث يستوعبون كل هذه الحقائق.
They could have a mental image of the cell
قد يستطيعون أخذ صورة ذهنية للخلية
as a large, bustling, hugely complicated city
كمدينة ضخمة، تعج بالحركة، شديدة التعقيد
that's occupied by micro-machines.
المليئة بالماكينات المتناهية في الصغر (مايكرو).
And these micro-machines really are at the heart of life.
وهذه الماكينات المتناهية في الصغر هي حقيقة قلب الحياة.
These micro-machines,
هذه الماكينات المتناهية في الصغر،
which are the envy of nanotechnologists the world over,
التي هي موضع حسد من تكنولوجيا النانو في جميع أنحاء العالم،
are self-directed, powerful, precise, accurate devices
تدار ذاتياً، بإقتدار، بدقة، أجهزة دقيقة
that are made out of strings of amino acids.
مصنوعة من أوتار من أحماض الأمينو.
And these micro-machines power how a cell moves.
وهذه الماكينات المتناهية في الصغر تحكم حركات الخلية،
They power how a cell replicates. They power our hearts.
تحكم كيف تتماثل الخلية، تحكم قلوبنا،
They power our minds.
تحكم عقولنا.
And so what we wanted to do was to figure out
وعليه، فأن ما أردنا معرفته
how we could make this story into an animation
هو كيفية تحويل القصة الى رسوم متحركة
that would be the centerpiece of BioVisions at Harvard,
والتي ستكون النقطة المركزية لبايو فيشن (BioVisions) في هارفارد،
which is a website that Harvard has
الذي هو موقع إلكتروني لدى هارفارد
for its molecular and cellular biology students
لطلابها من أقسام البيولوجي الجزيئية والخلوية
that will -- in addition to all the textual information,
الذي سيقوم -- بالإضافة الى كل المعلومات النصية،
in addition to all the didactic stuff --
بالإضافة الى كل فريق التدريس--
put everything together visually, so that these students
بوضع كل شئ سوياً بصورة مرئية، بحيث يستطيع
would have an internalized view of what a cell really is
أولئك الطلاب أخذ نظرة من الداخل لماهية الخلية
in all of its truth and beauty, and be able to study
بكل حقائقها وجمالها، ويستطيعوا دراستها
with this view in mind, so that their imaginations would be sparked,
مع هذا في أذهانهم، بحيث يتفتق خيالهم،
so that their passions would be sparked
وعليه تتفتق عواطفهم
and so that they would be able to go on
وكنتيجة لذلك سيكون بمقدورهم المضي قدماً
and use these visions in their head to make new discoveries
وإستخدام هذه الرؤى القابعة في أذهانهم لإكتشافات جديدة
and to be able to find out, really, how life works.
وأن يكون بمقدورهم معرفة، حقيقة، كيف تسير الحياة.
So we set out by looking at how these molecules are put together.
لذا فقد حددنا ذلك بالنظر في كيفية وضع هذه الجزيئات معاً.
We worked with a theme, which is, you've got macrophages
عملنا تحت شعار، لدينا ماكروفيجات (macrophages)
that are streaming down a capillary,
التي تنساب أسفل عبر أنبوب شعري،
and they're touching the surface of the capillary wall,
وهي تلامس سطح حائط الأنبوب الشعري،
and they're picking up information from cells
وهي تأخذ المعلومات من الخلايا
that are on the capillary wall, and they are given this information
الموجودة في حائط الأنبوب الشعري، وتعطيها هذه المعلومات
that there's an inflammation somewhere outside,
بأن هناك إلتهاب في مكان ما في الخارج،
where they can't see and sense.
حيث لا تستطيع النظر أو الإستشعار.
But they get the information that causes them to stop,
لكنها تتلقى المعلومات التي تفيدها بالتوقف،
causes them to internalize that they need to make
تجعلها تستوعب أنها بحاجة لصنع
all of the various parts that will cause them to change their shape,
كل الأجزاء المتعددة التي تتسبب في جعلها تغير شكلها،
and try to get out of this capillary and find out what's going on.
وتحاول أخذ هذه الأنابيب الشعرية لمعرفة ما يجري.
So these molecular motors -- we had to work
إذاً هذه المحركات الجزيئية -- توجب علينا العمل
with the Harvard scientists and databank models
مع علماء هارفارد ونماذج بنوك البيانات
of the atomically accurate molecules
لجزيئات الذرة الدقيقة
and figure out how they moved, and figure out what they did.
ومعرفة كيفية حركتها، ومعرفة ما فعلته.
And figure out how to do this in a way
ومعرفة كيفية عمل هذا بطريقة
that was truthful in that it imparted what was going on,
تكون حقيقية تقدم ما كان يحدث،
but not so truthful that the compact crowding in a cell
لكنها ليست حقيقية بنفس إزدحام وضغط الخلية
would prevent the vista from happening.
لأنه سيمنع العرض من الحدوث.
And so what I'm going to show you is a three-minute
وإذاً ما سأقوم به هو عرض ثلاث دقائق
Reader's Digest version of the first aspect of this film
نموذج أولي لأول جانب من هذا الفيلم
that we produced. It's an ongoing project
الذي أنتجناه. وهو مشروع ما يزال جارياً
that's going to go another four or five years.
وسيستمر أربعة الى خمسة سنوات لاحقة.
And I want you to look at this
وأريد منكم إلقاء نظرة على هذا
and see the paths that the cell manufactures --
ومشاهدة الدروب التي تصنعها الخلية--
these little walking machines, they're called kinesins --
هذه الماكينات الصغيرة التي تمشي، تسمى كينسانس (kinesins)--
that take these huge loads
التي تأخذ هذه الأحمال الضخمة
that would challenge an ant in relative size.
التي قد تساوي نملة في حجم نسبي.
Run the movie, please.
أبدأ الفيلم، رجاءً.
But these machines that power the inside of the cells
لكن هذه الماكينات التي تعمل داخل الخلايا
are really quite amazing, and they really are the basis of all life
فعلاً مدهشة جداً، وهي حقاً أساس كل الحياة.
because all of these machines interact with each other.
لأن كل هذه الماكينات تتفاعل مع بعضها البعض.
They pass information to each other.
يقدمون المعلومات لبعضهم البعض;
They cause different things to happen inside the cell.
يسببون أشياء مختلفة لتحدث داخل الخلية.
And the cell will actually manufacture the parts that it needs
وستقوم الخلية في الواقع بتصنيع الأجزاء التي تحتاجها
on the fly, from information
على الفور، من المعلومات
that's brought from the nucleus by molecules that read the genes.
التي أستقتها من نواة الجزيئات التي تقرأ الجينات.
No life, from the smallest life to everybody here,
لا حياة، من أصغر أنواع الحياة لأي شخص هنا،
would be possible without these little micro-machines.
ستكون ممكنة بدون هذه الماكينات المتناهية في الصغر.
In fact, it would really, in the absence of these machines,
في الحقيقة، سيكون حقاً، في غياب هذه الماكينات،
have made the attendance here, Chris, really quite sparse.
قد أحدث حضوراً هنا، كريس، حقيقة ، ضئيل جداً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Music)
(موسيقى)
This is the FedEx delivery guy of the cell.
هذا هو عامل توصيل فيديكس للخلية:
This little guy is called the kinesin,
يسمى هذا الشئ الصغير كينسين (kinesin)،
and he pulls a sack that's full of brand new manufactured proteins
ويقوم بسحب كيس من كل البروتينات المصنعة حديثاً
to wherever it's needed in the cell --
لأي محتاج لها في الخلية--
whether it's to a membrane, whether it's to an organelle,
سواء كان ذلك على الغشاء ، سواء كان ذلك لعضية،
whether it's to build something or repair something.
سواء كانت شئ لبناء شئ أو لإصلاح شئ.
And each of us has about 100,000 of these things
ولدى كل واحد منا حوالي مائة ألف من هذه الأشياء
running around, right now,
تعمل في الجوار، الآن،
inside each one of your 100 trillion cells.
داخل كل خلية من المائة تريلليون خلية لدينا.
So no matter how lazy you feel,
غض النظر عن مدى الكسل الذي تشعر به،
you're not really intrinsically doing nothing.
جوهرياً أنت تقوم بفعل شئ ما.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So what I want you to do when you go home
إذاً فما أريدكم أن تفعلوه حينما تعودوا الى البيت
is think about this, and think about how powerful our cells are.
هو أن تفكروا حول الأمر، وفكروا في قوة خلايانا،
And think about some of the things
وفكروا حول بعض الأشياء
that we're learning about cellular mechanics.
التي نتعلمها حول ماكينات الخلايا.
Once we figure out all that's going on --
بمجرد أن نعرف كيف يسير كل هذا--
and believe me, we know almost a percent of what's going on --
وصدقوني، نحن نعرف تقريباً واحد في المائة مما يجري--
once we figure out what's going on,
بمجرد أن نعرف ما يجري،
we're really going to be able to have a lot of control
سيكون بمقدورنا حقيقةً إكتساب الكثير من التحكم
over what we do with our health,
في ما نفعله بصحتنا،
with what we do with future generations,
في ما نفعله مع الأجيال المستقبلية،
and how long we're going to live.
كم سنعيش.
And hopefully we'll be able to use this
ونأمل أن نكون قادرين على إستخدام هذا
to discover more truth, and more beauty.
لإكتشاف حقائق أكثر، وجمال أكثر.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
But it's really quite amazing that these cells, these micro-machines,
لكن الأكثر إدهاشاً هو أن هذه الخلايا، هذه الماكينات المتناهية الصغر،
are aware enough of what the cell needs that they do their bidding.
مدركة بما يكفي لما تحتاجة الخلية بحيث تفعل دورها.
They work together. They make the cell do what it needs to do.
يعملون سوياً; يدفعون الخلية لفعل ما هو مطلوب منها.
And their working together helps our bodies --
وعملها الجماعي يساعد أجسامنا--
huge entities that they will never see -- function properly.
وحدات ضخمة لا يمكن رؤيتها-- تعمل بطريقة سليمة.
Enjoy the rest of the show. Thank you.
أستمتعوا ببقية العرض. شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)